A Finding Aid to the W.G. Constable Papers, 1905-1983, bulk 1920-1976, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
W.G. Constable papers
1905-1983
bulk 1920-1976
Archives of American Art
Constable, W. G. (William George), 1887-1976
AAA.conswmgp
Archival Resource Key
25.7 Linear feet
The papers of art historian and museum curator W.G. (William George) Constable measure 25.7 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1981, with the bulk of the material from 1920 to 1976. The papers include biographical material; professional and personal correspondence; extensive lectures, writings, and notes; exhibition and book research files; printed materials; and photographs, glass plate negatives, and slides. There is substantive correspondence related to Constable's participation in the American Defense Harvard Group and about the formation of the Roberts Commission, including correspondence with Ralph Perry, Hugh Hencken, Paul Sachs and George L. Stout. There are numerous official reports prepared by Constable after World War II for the U. S. Office of Military Government for Germany.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 10 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1905-1983 (1.2 linear feet; Box 1-2, OV 28)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1906-1981 (6.2 linear feet; Box 2-8, OV 28-29)
Series 3: Lectures, 1909-1963 (4.6 linear feet; Box 8-12)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1910-1974 (2 linear feet; Box 13-14)
Series 5: American Defense Harvard Group, 1942-1946 (0.6 linear feet; Box 15)
Series 6: Office of Military Government for Germany, 1947-1952 (0.3 linear feet; Box 15)
Series 7: Exhibition Files, 1930-1969 (1 linear foot; Box 15-16, OV 29)
Series 8: Research Files, 1922-1976 (7.5 linear feet; Box 16-24, OV 28-29)
Series 9: Printed Material, 1921-1977 (0.5 linear feet; Box 24)
Series 10: Photographic Materials, circa 1940-1960 (1.4 linear feet; Box 24-27, OV 28-29)
Biographical / Historical
W. G. (William George) Constable (1887-1976) was a museum curator and art historian who worked in England and Boston.
Born in Derby, England, Constable studied for the bar at Cambridge University, but was encouraged to pursue art over law by the Lord Chancellor who told him that law would be too strenuous after a two year convalescence from gassing during World War I. For three years, he studied at the Slade School and the Bartlett School of Architecture. In 1923, he joined the National Gallery of London where he became the Assistant Director in 1929. In 1930, he accepted the first Director's position at the newly formed Courtauld Institute, where he worked to develop one of the first programs on art history. In 1938, Constable became Curator of Paintings at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts and worked there until his retirement in 1957.
Throughout his career as an arts administrator, Constable remained an accomplished lecturer and held appointments as the Slade Professor of Art at Cambridge (1933-1936), Ryerson Lecturer at Yale University (1940), and the Lowell Lecturer at the Lowell Insitute (1958). As a researcher and art historian, he published a steady stream of essays on European and American art connoisseurship, and authored over ten scholarly books, including The Painter's Workshop (1953), Richard Wilson (1953), and Canaletto (1962), the definitive work on the Venetian master.
Constable was a trusted arts advisor and, in this capacity, worked for the Wadsworth Atheneum from 1943-1945. He also worked closely with Lord Beaverbrook to establish the National Gallery of Canada and later consulted for Sotheby's and the U. S. Internal Revenue Service.
In the years leading to World War II, Constable served as an advisor to the American Defense Harvard Group and was later appointed to the Commission for the Protection of Artistic and Historic Monuments in Europe (the Roberts Commission) by President Roosevelt. The Roberts Commission was responsible for the establishment of the U. S. Army's Monuments, Fine Arts, and Archives section. After the war, Constable served the U.S. government as a member of a commission responsible for the recovery of looted art work and the evaluation of the state of the arts in Germany and Italy.
After his retirement from the Boston Museum, Constable continued to research and write, and also served as president of the International Institute of Conservation (1958-1960) and the Renaissance Society of America (1959-1961). From 1957 to 1966, he worked on behalf of Christie's auction house, where he met with prospective clients and provided preliminary valuations of private art works and collections.
On February 4, 1976, Constable died in Cambridge, Massachusetts from natural causes.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and not served to researchers.
Existence and Location of Copies
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2016 and is available on the Archives of American Art's website. Materials which have not been scanned include blank pages, blank versos of photographs, and duplicates. Negatives and slides of artwork in Series 2, 4, 5, and 8 have not been scanned. In some cases, exhibition catalogs and other publications have had their covers, title pages, and relevant pages scanned.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of W.G. Constable were donated in multiple gifts from 1978 to 1979 and in 1987 to 1988 by his son Giles Constable. Additional material regarding Constable's research on Canaletto was donated by researcher J.G. Links in 1985.
Related Materials
The Archives also holds additional materials related to W.G. Constable, including an oral history interview with Constable conducted by Robert Brown in 1972-1973, and a photograph and clipping of Constable donated by Eleanor Barton in 1982.
Additional W.G. Constable papers are located at archival materials are also located at St. Johns College in Cambridge,England; the Warburg Institute in London, England; the National Gallery in London, England; and the Society for the Protection of Science and Learning in London, England. Photographs of works art collected by Constable are found at the British Studies Center at Yale University. Records relating to his tenure at the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston are housed there.
Scope and Contents
The papers of art historian and museum curator W.G. (William George) Constable measure 25.7 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1981, with the bulk of the material from 1920 to 1976. The papers include biographical material; professional and personal correspondence; extensive lectures, writings, and notes; exhibition and book research files; printed materials; and photographs, glass plate negatives, and slides. There is substantive correspondence related to Constable's participation in the American Defense Harvard Group and about the formation of the Roberts Commission, including correspondence with Ralph Perry, Hugh Hencken, Paul Sachs and George L. Stout. There are numerous official reports prepared by Constable after World War II for the U. S. Office of Military Government for Germany.
Biographical material includes W.G. Constable's curriculum vitae; club memberships; personal, educational, and military records; three memorial essays and obituaries; five address books; appointment books dating from 1930-1968; and financial records related to personal business travels.
Correspondence is mostly professional and arranged into General, Committee, Condolences, and J.G. Links. General correspondence is with friends, business associates, auction houses, galleries, and museums. The letters cover a wide variety of professional work, such as research projects, letters of inquiry and recommendation, and work done for Christie's and the Internal Revenue Service. Correspondents include Mortimer Brandt, Helen Frick, Helen Gluck, William Ivins, Duncan Phillips, Paul Sachs, and Rudolph Vasalle, among many others.
Committee related correspondence includes letters, memoranda, and reports related to ongoing committee objectives, projects, and routine activities. There is correspondence related to Constable's advisory work with the Art Gallery of Toronto, the National Gallery of Canada, and the Watts Gallery, among other projects. Condolences consists of letters and cards received by Constable's wife, Olivia, after Constable's death. Correspondence with J.G. Links is primarily about the second edition revision of Constable's book Canaletto.
There are over 170 drafts of Constable's notes and outlines for lectures. Topics range from 13th-20th century European and American art to museum conservation, ethics, art education, and art collecting. The series also includes lecture notes from organized touring trips to Canada, Northern Europe, Scandanavia, and Poland.
Writings consist of Constable's published and unpublished articles, articles submitted for the Encyclopedia of World Art, essays, notes, exhibition catalogs, translations, and drafts and research material related to Art Collecting in the United States, Art History and Connoisseurship, and The Painter's Workshop.
Files specifically documenting Constable's advisory role in the World War II American Defense Harvard Group drafting and organizing lists of men with curatorial, museum conservation, or library/archives backgrounds to aid in the protection European most valued cultural artifacts, artwork, and architecture. There are letters documenting the formation of the Harvard Group and its goals and objections. The files also include many of the original lists that were forwarded to the Commission for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in Europe, also known as the Roberts Commission, eventually leading to the formation of the U.S. Army's Monuments, Fine Arts, and Archives division. The series also includes the Harvard Group's manual Safeguarding and Conserving Cultural Materials in the Field, committee minutes, and clippings related to their work. Correspondents include Ralph Perry, Paul Sachs, George L. Stout, and Hugh Hencken.
Constable's work after the war for the U.S. Office of Military Government for Germany is documented through numerous reports, memoranda, letters, and other official documents from the U. S. Army to Constable about surveying the state of German and Italian art institutions after World War II. The series also includes Constable's notebook "Visits in Germany" (1949), and a copy of his report Art and Reorientation: Status and Future of Museums and the Teaching of Art in Western Germany.
Exhibition files contain correspondence, notes, lists, research material, and reports related to exhibitions that Constable organized prior to his employment by and after his retirement from the Boston Museum of Art.
Research files contain materials relevant to Constable's interests and include notes, lists, correspondence, and printed and photographic reference material. These subject areas cover artists, including extensive files on Canaletto and other vedute painters, museum conservation, museums and galleries, private and public art collections, and schools of art.
Printed materials include clippings, programs, book excerpts and other miscellaneous printed materials.
Photographic materials include prints of Constable with friends and family, as well as prints, glass negatives and slides of artwork. There are also prints of the Fogg Art Museum's interiors and exterior and interior shots of Tennessee Valley Authority dam projects.
Painters; Art, European; Art -- Study and teaching; Museum curators -- Massachusetts -- Boston; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Cultural property -- Conservation and restoration -- Germany; Cultural property -- Conservation and restoration -- Italy; Art -- Conservation and restoration; Art historians -- Massachusetts -- Boston; Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955); Museum curators -- England; World War, 1939-1945 -- Art and the war; Art historians -- England; National Gallery of Canada; Watts Gallery; Phillips, Duncan, 1886-1966; Christie, Manson & Woods International Inc.; Fogg Art Museum; Museum of Fine Arts, Boston; Stout, George L. (George Leslie); Canaletto, 1697-1768; Perry, Ralph; American Commission for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in War Areas; Sachs, Paul J. (Paul Joseph), 1878-1965; Hencken, Hugh O'Neill; Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone). Office of Military Government; Art Gallery of Toronto; Vasalle, Rudolph; United States. Internal Revenue Service; Brandt, Mortimer; Links, J. G.; Ivins, William Mills, 1881-1961; Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters. Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives Section; Frick, Helen Clay, 1888-1984; Gluck, Helen
- Biographical Materials, 1905-1983; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.2 Linear feet Box 1-2, OV 28
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes W.G. Constable's curriculum vitae, club memberships, and personal, educational, and military records, including passports, university exams and degrees, and a hair sample. The series also includes obituaries and three memorial essays written by friends and family; five address books; daily appointment books dating from 1930-1968; and financial records related to personal business travels.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Routine financial receipts have not been scanned.
  - Club Memberships, A-D, circa 1930-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Club Memberships, D-O, circa 1930-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Club Memberships, P-So, circa 1930-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Club Memberships, Sp-Z, circa 1930-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1950-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Employment Records, 1920-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Essay, "Tribute to W.G. Constable" by Walter Muir Whitehall, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Essay, "W.G. Constable" by Gardner Cox, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Essay, "W.G. Constable" by Giles Constable, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Examinations, Bar (Law), 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Oversized material housed in Box 28, Folder 1.
  - Examinations, University, 1905-1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hair Sample, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum of Agreement (Contracts), 1927-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Military Service Documents, 1916-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Obituary, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Passports, 1933-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - University Degrees, 1952-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Address Book, Great Britain, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Address Book, Great Britain, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Address Book, Europe, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Address Book, North America, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Address Book, North America, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Address Memorandum, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Appointment Books, 1930-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Appointment Books, 1936-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Appointment Books, 1941-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Appointment Books, 1945-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Appointment Books, 1949-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Appointment Books, 1953-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Appointment Books, 1957-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Appointment Books, 1961-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Appointment Books, 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Expense Books, 1906-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Financial Records, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Financial Records, 1936-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Financial Records, 1940-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Financial Records, 1945-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Financial Records, 1950-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Financial Records, 1956-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Financial Records, 1960-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records, 1977-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Oversize Legal Examination Certificate scanned with Box 1, Folder 10, 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Military Certificate scanned with Box 1, Folder 14, 1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 28, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1906-1981; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 6.2 Linear feet Box 2-8, OV 28-29
  Correspondence is primarily with Constable's friends and business associates discussing personal research projects, professional and committee related work, and letters of condolences.
  The series is arranged as 4 subseries:
  Missing Title
  2.1: General, 1906-1975
  2.2: Committees, 1924-1976
  2.3: Condolences, 1976-1979
  2.4: J.G. Links, 1964-1981
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Negatives and slides of artwork have not been scanned.
  - General, 1906-1975; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    Correspondence includes letters to friends and business associates discussing personal scholarly research, book projects, museum conservation techniques, letters of inquiry and recommendation, general appraisel requests, and work done for Christie's and the Internal Revenue Service. Correspondents of note include Helen Frick, Duncan Phillips, and Paul Sachs.
    - A Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Agnew, Doreen, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Alford, John, 1958-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - American Federation of Arts, 1957-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Ames, Winslow, 1958-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Apollo Magazine, 1957-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Art Gallery of Toronto, 1959-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Athenaeum, London, 1937-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Ba-Bn Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Bo-Bz Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Bacon, T.W., 1940-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Bacon, T.W., 1947-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1963-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Beacon Press, 1960-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Beacon Press, 1963-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Berger, Milton, 1959-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Bernard, Herbert C., 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Bolton, Guy, 1958-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Bowdain College Museum of Art, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Bradner, Leicester, 1949-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Brandt, Mortimer, 1955-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - British Council, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - British Foreign Office, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Burlington Magazine, 1923-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Butler, Beatrice, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - C Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Cambridgeshire Education Committee, 1935-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Canadian Art, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Cannon, Foster, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Centner, Charles W., 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1945-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1958 January; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1958 February-March; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1958 April-July; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1958 August-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1959 January-February; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1959 March; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1959 April-May; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1959 June-July; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1959 August; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1959 September; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1959 October; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1959 November-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1960 January-March; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1960 April-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1962 January-July; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1962 August-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1963 January-July; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1963 August-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Christie's (Christie, Manson and Woods Ltd.), 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - City of Auckland Art Gallery, 1958-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - College Art Association of America, 1957-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Courtould Institute of Art, 1930-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Courtould Institute of Art, 1932-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - D Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - De Beer Fine Art Ltd., 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Dedham Vale Society, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Detroit City of Fine Arts, 1961-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Drysdale, Susan, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Duncan, Louis G., 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - E Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Eastman Kodak Company, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - F Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Fitzwilliam Museum, 1937, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Fogg Art Museum (Coolidge, John), 1957-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)